Zitao(Jerry) Liu

CONTACT Information $\begin{array}{lll} \mbox{Department of Computer Science} & \mbox{\it Voice:} +1 \ (412) \ 614-0513 \\ \mbox{University of Pittsburgh} & \mbox{\it E-mail:} \ \mbox{\it ztliu@cs.pitt.edu} \\ \end{array}$

Pittsburgh, PA 15213 USA WWW: http://www.cs.pitt.edu/~ztliu

RESEARCH INTERESTS Machine Learning, specialized in Time Series, Probabilistic Graphical Model and Optimization. Plentiful industrial experience in Forecasting, Text Mining, Recommendation and Ranking.

EDUCATION

University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania USA

Ph.D. Candidate, Computer Science Expected graduation date: May 2016

- Dissertation Topic: "Time Series Modeling of Irregularly Sampled Multivariate Clinical Data"
- Advisor: Milos Hauskrecht (milos@cs.pitt.edu) GPA: 3.88/4.0
- Google Scholar Profile: http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=rRTzNmOAAAAJ

Wuhan University, Wuhan, Hubei China

B.Eng., Software Engineering May, 2010 GPA: 3.71/4.0

Industry Experience

Alibaba Group, Seattle, WA

Research Intern, Institute of Data Science and Technology

06/2015 - 08/2015

Designed and implemented a large scale user targeting and recommendation algorithm for Tmall (http://www.tmall.com/), which is the largest premier business-to-consumer online retail website in China. The algorithm is built on 10 billion highly sparse user behavior records (click, collect, cart, purchase information) involving 42 million users and 150 thousand shops. The algorithm includes a mix of collaborative filtering and pairwise learning to rank using logistic regression.

Yahoo! Lab, Sunnyvale, CA

Research Intern, Advertising Science Team

05/2014 - 08/2014

Analyzed the web page traffic time series using seasonal-trend decomposition. Implemented an ensemble time series forecasting model which involves SVM Regression, Regression Tree, Gaussian Process, Gradient Boosting Tree, Local Regression, etc. Proposed an iterative algorithm to accurately estimate the missing values for hierarchical time series, which outperforms state-of-art missing value estimation techniques like matrix factorization, matrix completion, local regression, probabilistic PCA, etc.

ebay Research Lab, San Jose, CA

Research Intern, Data Science Team

06/2013 - 08/2013

Performed a large scale query logs analysis for assessing personalization opportunities in eBay. Wrote Hadoop jobs to process 12 months (2012/08-2013/07) about 26 billion queries. Tried to answer questions like "What user information should we use in e-commerce websites to improve personalization?", "Should we do personalization on every query?", "Does recency effect will influence the personalized query prediction?"

Google, Mountain View, CA

Software Engineer Intern, Ads Review Team

06/2012 - 08/2012

Built feature extractors for advertisements from Google AdWords, which involves more than 50 languages. Built and applied classifiers to detect illegal and malevolent advertisement texts.

Journal Publications

Zitao Liu and Milos Hauskrecht. Clinical Time Series Prediction: Towards A Hierarchical Dynamical System Framework. *Artificial Intelligence in Medicine (AIIM)*, 2014.

Conference Publications

Zitao Liu and Milos Hauskrecht. Learning Linear Dynamical Systems from Multivariate Time Series: A Matrix Factorization Based Framework. *SIAM International Conference on Data Mining(SDM)*, 2016.

Zitao Liu and Milos Hauskrecht. Learning Adaptive Forecasting Models from Irregularly Sampled Multivariate Clinical Data. The 30th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2016.

Zitao Liu, Yan Yan, Jian Yang and Milos Hauskrecht. Missing Value Estimation for Hierarchical Time Series: A Study of Hierarchical Web Traffic. *The IEEE International Conference on Data Mining(ICDM)*, 2015.

Zitao Liu and Milos Hauskrecht. A Regularized Linear Dynamical System Framework for Multivariate Time Series Analysis. The 29th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2015.

Mahdi Pakdaman, Iyad Batal, **Zitao Liu**, CharmGil Hong and Milos Hauskrecht. An Optimization-based Framework to Learn Conditional Random Fields for Multi-label Classification. *SIAM International Conference on Data Mining(SDM)*, 2014.

Zitao Liu and Milos Hauskrecht. Clinical Time Series Prediction with a Hierarchical Dynamical System. 14th Conference on Artificial Intelligence in Medicine (AIME), 2013.

Zitao Liu, Lei Wu and Milos Hauskrecht. Modeling Clinical Time Series Using Gaussian Process Sequences. SIAM International Conference on Data Mining(SDM), 2013.

Zitao Liu, Wenchao Yu, Wei Chen, Shuran Wang and Fengyi Wu. Short Text Feature Selection and Classification for Micro Blog Mining. *International Conference on Computational Intelligence and Software Engineering(CiSE)*, 2010.

Zitao Liu, Wenchao Yu, Yalan Deng, Yongtao Wang and Zhiqi Bian. A Feature Selection Method for Document Clustering Based on Part-of-Speech and Word Co-Occurrence. *Proceedings of International Conference on Fuzzy Systems and Knowledge Discovery(FSKD)*, 2010.

Yang Shen, **Zitao Liu**, Cheng Luo and Ye Li. Research on Social Network Based on Meta-search Engine. *Proceedings of Web Information Systems and Applications Conference(WISA)*, 2009.

Yang Shen, **Zitao Liu**, Shaoji Luo, Huijuan Fu and Ye Li. Empirical Research on E-Government Based on Content Mining. *Proceedings of International Conference on Management of E-Commerce and E-Government(ICMeCG)*, 2009.

Workshop & Posters

Zitao Liu and Yan Yan. A Probabilistic Framework for Hierarchical Time Series Forecasting. *The 32nd International Conference on Machine Learning Workshop on Demand Forecasting (ICML-Workshop)*, 2015.

Zitao Liu, Gyanit Singh, Nish Parikh and Neel Sundaresan. A Large Scale Query Logs Analysis for Assessing Personalization Opportunities in E-commerce Sites. *ACM International Conference on Web Search and Data Mining Workshop on Log-Based Personalization (WSDM-Workshop)*, 2014.

Zitao Liu and Milos Hauskrecht. Sparse Linear Dynamical System with Its Application in Multivariate Clinical Time Series. *Neural Information Processing Systems Workshop on Machine Learning for Clinical Data Analysis and Healthcare (NIPS-Workshop)*, 2013.

Zitao Liu, Lei Wu and Milos Hauskrecht. State Space Gaussian Process Prediction. The 29th International Conference on Machine Learning Workshop on Clinical Data Analysis (ICML-Workshop), 2012.

Zitao Liu and Sangyeun Cho. Characterizing Machines and Workloads on a Google Cluster, Proceedings of the Eighth International Workshop on Scheduling and Resource Management for Parallel and Distributed Systems(SRMPDS), 2012.

Yang Shen, Huijuan Fu, Zitao Liu, Pengpeng Liu and Qingchuan Fu. Empirical Analysis on Chinese Academic Plagiarism. Proceedings of the 9th ACM/IEEE-CS Joint Conference on Digital Libraries(JCDL-Poster), 2009.

- Honors & Awards Aaai Student Travel Award 2016
 - Best Graduate Poster Award, University of Pittsburgh 2015
 - ICDM Student Travel Award 2015
 - Andrew Mellon Predoctoral Fellowship, University of Pittsburgh 2015
 - People's Choice Graduate Poster Winner, University of Pittsburgh 2015
 - Best Graduate Poster Runner-Up Award, University of Pittsburgh 2014
 - SDM Student Travel Award 2013, 2014
 - ICML Student Travel Award 2012
 - Arts and Sciences Fellowship, University of Pittsburgh 2010
 - Best Thesis Award of Bachelor's Degree, Ministry of Education of Hubei Province 2010
 - National Scholarship, Ministry of Education of China 2007, 2009
 - Citigroup Scholarship, Citigroup Services and Technology (China) Limited 2008

Academia Services

PC Member

- 11th International Conference on Machine Learning and Data Mining
- 7th Asian Conference on Intelligent Information and Database Systems
- 12th, 13th International Conference on Signal Processing and Multimedia Applications

Journal Reviewer

- ACM Transactions on Intelligent Systems and Technology
- IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems
- Applied Clinical Informatics
- Artificial Intelligence in Medicine
- Computers and Electrical Engineering
- International Journal of Science, Technology and Society

External Reviewer: AAAI2016, ICML2015, NIPS2015, SDM2015, AAAI2015, CIKM2014, ICDM2014, ICDM2013

Teaching EXPERIENCE

University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania USA

Teaching Assistant

- CS2610 Interface Design and Evaluation (Fall 2012)
- CS1571 Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (Fall 2012)
- CS2750 Machine Learning (Spring 2012)
- CS0441 Discrete Structures for Computer Science (Fall 2011, Spring 2013)
- CS0401 Intermediate Programming Using Java (Spring 2011)